Thank you. All right. Good afternoon, everybody. I'll call the meeting of the government study transition committee to order And I did I take roll call you take roll call doesn't get Mayor Sriracha here Counselor Ahmed Our solicitor is here And I'm here as the chair John McRann. Could I have an Approve we have two sets of minutes. Can I approve them? In one motion. All right. Can I ask for approval of the minutes of both the May 6th and July 29th meetings? Okay, thank you very much Yeah, can we have an update on the administrative code sure
so I met with City Council's Committee of the Whole on four different occasions for specially set meetings of the committee to discuss the code in two tranches
So we met on June 17th, July 15th, August 19th and September 16th at the conclusion of the first two meetings the first tranche which was presented by consensus was Agreed upon to be moved into the formal code which will then come to City Council again for adoption
And then the same thing happened at the end of the September 16th meeting where the second tranche, by consensus, we have a consensus that we're good to move forward.
The one gap in that administrative code was the ethics code, which is obviously next on your agenda. Okay. And so if you're all right, I'll lump the two together in my review. Yep, that sounds great. Thank you. Following appointments to the commission from council, the mayor, and the controller, I've met with the Ethics Commission on four separate meetings, August 7th, September 4th,
September 25th, and October 16th, during which we discussed all of the various provisions that they might want to see included in an ethics code. And so in compliance with the charter, they approved a memorandum that I'll be submitting to council with their recommendations. and there's a public workshop scheduled now for November 6th which is next week at which I'll follow the similar path that I followed with the admin code which is I've taken those recommendations and I've drafted a proposed code and we'll walk through both the recommendations
and the code at the public workshop on November 6th. We'll do that one a little bit differently
then we've done the others in other words we'll stop at each section and open each section up the public comment since it is a public workshop and not uh meant to be as much of a one one table of discussion just among council members um and so they'll hopefully be a little bit of interactive discussion with with the public uh who chooses to weigh in as we go through each section in the ethics code ultimately the goal here is to have that um a consensus reached on that as well and and move that into the admin code which would then come back to
council as an ordinance in December okay with the concept being to present that
ordinance at the December committee meeting now council have already seen
you know all of the language in the admin code and the ethics code but
they'll now see it sort of in one final document and then it would go through a first and a second reading just as any other ordinance would. This keeps us on target to meet two dates that are set up in the charter for compliance one of which is adoption of an ethics code by December 31st and the other is adoption of an admin code within 18 months of the beginning of the year and so we're going to exceed the 18 months which was the goal all along was to try and get that up and running as quickly as possible, and for the ethics code. I will note for this committee that one of the recommendations that came from the ethics commission is that they essentially take the first year to educate elected officials, employees, and potential officials of
the code because there is a this is a new requirement and to give them time to
set the processes up for being able to handle complaints handle investigations
and do all the things that a code would require it is relatively unrealistic to expect that a code be set up that says there's going to be a complaint process
and to be able to have that up and running when you adopt it in mid to late december and have it up and running in january so that that is one of the recommendations that's
gonna it's coming from the ethics commission directly doesn't mean that the code doesn't exist it means there's a time to roll it out in a way that works uh effectively and they could do it faster if all things work out if the stars align could be in it could be ready to be in place with complaint procedures investigators hired all of the things that need to be done website access all of the things that will come could be done faster than a year but they want to make sure that they have the time to do it correctly so okay is there i i have a question or two but i'll let you is that do you have more to tell us so there's a little bit more in conjunction with the admin code ordinance there'll be a series of other ordinances that'll to be presented in December one of which is an ordinance to deal with the abolition of the treasurer position which came about as part of the charter the treasurer you know the treasurer's duties obligations roles boards they served on are set in multiple places in the current city code so we need to deal with all of those at the same time because the current treasurer's term of
office expires at the end of this year. So if you recall the charter provided that upon the expiration of the current treasurer's term there would no longer be the office of treasurer. So
there is an ordinance that will be presented to council in December that deals with that along with inclusions in the budget ordinance for funding the ethics commission and some of the things they need to do and with some proposals from the staff in the form of
ordinances for consolidating a number of our boards to create one appeals board
to hear appeals of the various items that happen that get appealed currently get appealed currently to a number of separate boards and commissions now that
is not something that was mandated by the Charter but the the Charter's concept of trying to make sure we have qualified people to do the work that's
needed for boards and commissions prompted a review of those items okay so that's that's the sum of my report okay what all what what appeal boards will be right there's property maintenance housing and what that what the concept is and Barry jump in about this right is that they'll basically be a group pool of that can be used to hear appeals on various topics but that we won't have to have people assigned to each and every one of those so instead of having like some general people who are procedurally sound and like okay let's hear the appeal this is what information you need to submit we're gonna review this and then having technical people there to respond we have to have all of those people on all of those boards which at a minimum is three usually they're five to seven so nine times seven at the high end nine times three at the low end to one group of people that we can yeah
it's just activate yeah yeah and and the appeals boards don't get activated regularly so what this also does is allow us to have consistency and how appeals are handled both procedurally which which is more transparent more accountable to the member of the public there's a procedure they're all going to know to follow when an appeal is filed it'll allow those boards to be better trained and better equipped to handle an appeal when they come and to make sure that both the
boards uh and staff are better prepared whether that's through assignment of council to represent the board and assignment of council to represent staff it allows for a a much more orderly process which i think will be to the benefit of both those appealing and to the city who is receiving the appeals yeah no i think that's brilliant um i mean i've got to serve for a while on the building code board of appeals and you know that at that time anyway was somewhat active you know we wouldn't have an appeal every month but you know every second or third um to the best of my knowledge i'm still a member of the stormwater board of appeals yes but once we had one hearing one hearing one time maybe my 2014. yes it might maybe my first year yeah so um you know so that sounds like a load off of my plate yes so yeah no that's yeah now you know depending on the administrivia of all of that um because they expire and then they have to get renewed they have to go to council so then council's like touching paper bernie's mr harris is touching paper the mayor's office it's just yeah no that sounds like a pretty brilliant idea so that's great my only question on that is if there is like a stormwater board a stormwater appeal that comes like how is the process of selecting who the experts are in that particular area okay so um the simple answer is have you ever been to court yes okay um do you think the judge was a subject matter expert in the area you were yes i i can guarantee you they probably were not yeah um the reason i say that is that that's essentially like that is the court system when you go to a magisterial district judge right now and we're bringing a say a enforcement action related to the sidewalk ordinance they don't know anything about our sidewalk ordinance they don't necessarily know the laws related to sidewalk maintenance it's their job to hear the facts from both and then to find and apply the law but now with the appeals board that
still applies but because we do have experts in various subject matter the goal will be to have a panel so that there'll be at least one subject matter
expert on each panel assuming from the community correct assuming that we can get them to have time available to hold an appeal within the set time frames which will be 60 days but that's the concept is we don't want to eliminate the expertise but the expertise is not necessarily not necessarily a
requirement and sometimes it can be a detriment until until their terms expire
and then the way it's being set up is that the appeals board will consist of at least seven members so currently there are more that there will be more than seven some of whose people those some of those members terms are going to expire and then it will be a determination as to whether to continue to reappoint them or not there will be six or seven mandated experts that have to be kept that we have to have on the panel on the board of appeal panel at all times so we'll need to have at least one or two that are versant in building codes property issues a couple others that to be consistent with uniform construction code property maintenance code some of the sewer code issues that we're dealing with but the goal is not to kick anybody off that's on and currently you know if if we have that combined board and we've got a housing board appeal you would start with trying to get a panel of people that were appointed for housing board because that was what their interest was you know but again one of the issues is always scheduling so we don't have set times for these appeal hearings so the volunteers haven't necessarily carved
out a particular time of the month every month to meet and so we want to be able to make this so do you think it'll turn out that there is an appeals board meeting most months there will be my guess is that we'll end up with at least six to twelve
a year okay yep and so i i would think that yes the answer is there'll be enough it would be great if they were like at this right time yeah and then people knew like if they yeah and it would save some of the as the mayor said a lot of the administration about trying to find a meeting date and time that works for everybody those who are appealing will know immediately whoever their people are that they're bringing to help them at the hearing are going to have to be available for that that time those are those are the those are the administrative benefits i'll be honest to me the benefits are about having a trained appeals board
having consistency having a set procedure that's very transparent and and consistently applied is
of immense benefit to those who are going through city processes and for the city staff who have to figure out what to do when an appeal comes in well and also you know and as you know and seven you know in the long run seven people instead of nine times three or five you know i mean or seven yeah i mean that to me like i mean i think about that a lot you know the burden of filling all of these board commission authority seats with from our you know city population that's not that it is consistent with the Charter and that the Charter encouraged using a process similar to what we did with the Ethics Commission for creating and finding appointments and this this may be a place where you know we might not have an opening on a board currently that that somebody is you know dying to be on but might be willing to serve on this one as a sort of an introduction or a means to city to help the city so there's a lot of flexibility so for the for the critical meetings for the past for passing these ordinance what are the dates of those December meetings so
December committee meeting is I think is December 3rd of Monday okay first and
second readings so it is a little bit more compressed schedule because of the holiday the holiday week and the other important date to note is the public work session for the ethics commission is on November the 6th yeah so the expectation is that you know pending you know councils process most likely
expecting pet these to all of this bundle of things to pass on December 16
well clearly the admin code and the ethics code the ethics codes requirements so you know if council wants to hold out must right correct so So if council, you know, doesn't like the rest of the admin code and wants to pull out the ethics code, they can. But the sense that we've received from the work we've done with council already is that this should be able to be molded into one document. And if things don't follow exactly, you know, there's still two weeks in December. Old special meetings, but yeah. If necessary, a special meeting could be convened to meet the ethics code deadline for sure. On Christmas Day, we'll have the special meeting. 23rd the 23rd and the 30th
I've had meetings with other municipalities. I'm not I'm not proposing that I'm just I'm just making sure that
No, oh I agree, I'm just making I'm just I'm just trying to make sure I understand how Yes, our job is to make sure we meet the deadline yes and that that in the event that there's that there's a little bit of cushion in case things aren't complete on the 60 the whip has been over my head to meet the deadline and okay sure the charters the whip that's right yeah yeah okay yeah no that's great so is so in the other thing I went so with the Ethics Commission do they do they expect to continue to follow a regular schedule of meetings throughout at least some of 2026 to do this additional work that they talked about well that'll be the part that they need to work on next yeah we'll start with that they have another meeting in December I think it's the 6 but I'm not positive off the top without looking but their next meeting are going to start talking about their own internal organization now so they can
start discussing meeting schedules they can start discussing bylaws they can start discussing the concept of education with the with the expectation hope that the code will follow the recommendations they've made obviously they will need the final determination which is the the adoption of the code itself by council but yes that is that is an expectation that they
will probably be meeting regularly in 2026. okay that's what that schedule is i don't know yet yeah okay excellent um that's the end of my questions any other questions from the committee no my questions were answered and yeah i mean i'll just ask as a council i we have the strong impression that the based on the questions in the company yeah yeah i think so as well from also my
perception of the other councils i think i think it was this work sessions were beneficial to go
through it and iron out any wrinkles or questions good so I think we shouldn't have any problems I mean I think any any last-minute things because now council has had this for months and then that then the Ethics Commission is really the newest piece plus this conversation about the board consolidation so there There'll be two new pieces coming to council in December that we'll just need. We'll have a committee meeting about, so they'll be presented at the committee meeting. Will we get the memo on the Ethics Commission at the meeting on the 6th, or will that be at the committee meeting? My hope is to have it to council the memo at least in advance of the meeting. So you should get it the Thursday before the 3rd when the board packets go out, whatever date that is. so that is the plan is i'm having a draft i have to finish it uh um it would be november the 27th you would have the board packet for the december 1st committee meeting which would include the memo from the ethics commission no no the memo for the ethics commission will be before the public work session oh right sorry so you have that too my goal is to get that out early next week oh gotcha okay i i don't know that i'll get it out tomorrow or friday yet but my goal is by early next yeah so it won't be on the november city council agenda but it will be on the december city council agenda but the work session you'll have it before that got it and and the goal like i said the goal is to walk through the ethics code the same way we did with uh uh admin code the difference here is instead of you know 40 pages at a time we're really talking about
far more limited section and there there there will be some educational
components as John can tell you there's there's a little as they looked at these
there's some a lot of its definitional and understanding of process and understanding what legally you can and can't do with elected officials so
that's the process we've been working on with the Ethics Commission to get to their recommendation so we'll do some of that as part of the public workshop as well what was the public engagement like through you know reviewing these tranches and with the ethics Commission was it was there was there a participation there was a little bit with the admin code there wasn't much with the ethics code okay then you know I had one other sort of a little bit off-topic question is there anything else to talk about with either the updates on the administrative code or on the ethics Commission okay I was just curious I was I can't believe I forgot about this but I was so excited to see the introduction of the budget and yeah how what's how are our feelings about that I think staff feels good about breaking up the content and not plowing through it all day on a Saturday I think it's giving a little bit more space to have some additional dialogue um uh meeting the timeline was okay um we're we um we're down to the wire on posting the water fund budget so we're going to share that by friday per the per the home roll charter so there were some delays in getting that prepared but we're this is a heads up to you that there's a memo coming related to the water fund in advance of the 18th um the session on the 18th but from a staff perspective i think it's been great i mean it was manageable yeah some people felt they stopped they drew the short straw having to go in october but in terms of what their presentation was but then i think generally there's so much work at the end of this particular year i think it's just going to give in future years a space to like actually not be looking at the budget over thanksgiving holiday and to be able to have a little bit more downtime in in december knowing that there's been time to work through everything great yeah i mean i think from a council perspective i think it's been very helpful to get it earlier and to get more engagement with it earlier both as from council and from the public um and then it kind of again gets us to kind of think about any questions or anything that anything that we see in the budget that we may have you know some opinions or questions on i think it allows more engagement which was the whole purpose of getting it earlier in the home rule charter i think the only other thing i would add to that is that because there are no rate increases being proposed either from property tax earned income tax or any of the enterprise funds that this is a little bit of a quieter budget but i think that there are some very very significant aspects of the budget that council is going to need to weigh in on that are different um just given just a bunch of different sort of things like the end of arpa and some of the other things that we've been working on um that just are going to make this one a little different so i think there's more opportunity for council to engage without having without it being like being pushed from a you need to lower tax rates you need to lower you know what i mean yeah okay this
is our last meeting right this is this is um actually the conclusion uh john of uh a lot of
great work by you and the rest of the commission the study commission all right then um i thank you for uh coordinating these meetings and and holding us to to meeting the deadlines and and all the work you did to get there. So it's been a pleasure and an honor. Yeah, yeah, well, that's great. Yeah, no, thanks. And yeah, I mean, I appreciate how straightforward this work was and that most of the administrative code and all the rest of it got done smoothly and easily. So yeah, so that's great. I mean, just while we're at it, I mean, Are there any other, you know, other than the, you know, what we just talked about with the budget, any other observations from, you know, the, from, you know, mayor, council or, you know, as far as just, you know, you know, how the implement, you know, how this transition has gone and, you know, is it, are, are we, you know, is, you know, nice and smooth, bumps, you know, finding, I mean, it's exciting to find a little, a little gem like, you know, consolidating the, the appeals boards, stuff like that.
So I would say, you know, we're not going to find out the bumps until next year and the years after because, as you recall, what we did is adopt an ordinance that basically said the third class city code was in place until the admin code was adopted. So I think some of the bumps will start to arise, if any, in the year and or years to come.
I think we're also going to see at times that there are some limitations that we didn't have under our third class city code designation that we will have with the home rule charter designation, and those are going to take some staff really managing and thinking through
how we do things, and then that's going to impact legislation, and that's particularly
in the caveat that as a home rule municipality, we can't legislate business. and so that is going to have an impact at some point in some ways but to date it's been a pleasure working with council and the appointed ethics commission so from my perspective that's been smooth i don't think the abolition of the treasurer is going to cause any consternation because of the way we were set up already in terms of how those functions were handled so i think it will continue to be smooth with just some anticipated there's always people that will raise something about the law or something along the lines that that's going to come up i think it also just provides an opportunity for future council and administration to dive into updating ordinances because we have not really done a lot of updating during my time as mayor in large measure because we've been focused on you know home rules consumed a lot of this and And also, the pieces of legislation that we focused on were very specifically around policy priorities, like the lead ordinance and housing, specifically some elements related to Vision Zero. But I think that there is a need to really review the other specific ordinances that weren't touched as part of admin code to both bring them into compliance. i think there's a lot of work ahead um but they'll that but there is it can be taken um in bite size rather than through the process that we just went through i mean i agree and i think through the home rule study commission process there was a lot of public engagement and a lot of discussion which i appreciated because it made this process a lot smoother where it wasn't as much contention or questions it was more like okay we already agreed on this in the charter and now this is our driving document for you know the future so great excellent well good i think that feels like we're good well a job well done yeah right yeah there you go and we have no public so there's no opportunity for public comment so i'll make I'll take a motion to adjourn all right thanks so much everybody